Hi there, and in this video I'm gonna
show you the importance of using tests.
So as you can see at the moment, I've
got a very simple calculator class and
attached to that calculator class is a
method that adds two values together.
So as you can see, the method up here
shows us that we are taking in two integers
and we're gonna return what would happen
if we add those two integers together?
Down here we are calling that method and
we're gonna pop it into a new variable called
total, and we're gonna output the total.
So if I was to test this manually, I
would press this button here, run it, and
as you can see, I'm getting the result.
Four.
If I change this to a three and run
it, you should see that I'll get a five
and I'm happy with that, that works.
But if I was to multiply that up by
a hundred times, if I had a hundred
methods that I was testing, I might not
be so satisfied with doing it that way.
It would be very time consuming and every
time I made a change, I would have to go
back and run all those tests manually again.
So it'll be really handy to have an
autonomous process that can do it for me.
And we've actually got that.
So what I'm going to do is I'm gonna
come up to file, I'm gonna look
for a library that does just that.
So I'm gonna go into project structure and I'm
gonna go to libraries add, maven and the library
I'm gonna look for is called J Unit and the one
I'm particularly interested in is called Jupiter.
So I'm gonna look for J Unit Jupiter, and I'm
just gonna hit this little magnifier over here.
And what will happen is it will search the
Maven directory for that, that library.
So let's just see if it finds it and it's found
quite a few Now the one that I'm interested.
Is this one here, it's 5.9 0.1.
I'm not gonna go for a snapshot, I'm
just gonna go for the full version.
So that's the one I'm going to use.
It tells me where it's going to pop it,
so I'm gonna go, okay, and it's gonna
associate it with the test project.
As you can see, I'm calling it test up
here, so I'm okay with that and these
are all the files that are required.
They're all JAR files these are Java.
Okay it.
I'm happy with that.
Now it doesn't just stop there because
I need my tests to go somewhere.
So let's go back into the project structure.
This time, I'm gonna go into modules.
Now at the moment, as you can see, SRC is blue
because it's a source file the system knows that
but you can see I have another one called tests.
So let's create a test file and what I'm gonna
do is I'm gonna make it a sub folder of src.
I'm gonna right click on src, go to
new directory and call it tests like
so and I've kept it lowercase cause
all the others are lowercase as well.
So I'm gonna click okay.
Now what's happened is I've got this
little expansion tool open up on src.
So let's just press on it and you can
see I've got now a folder called Tests.
Now tests is not associated with anything but
the top I've got a test option, so what I'm
gonna do is I'm gonna click on it and what you'll
see over here on the right, it's now associated
SRC backslash tests as a test source folder
that's exactly what I want, So I click okay.
Now, if I come up to here, I've now got
a test folder, which I'm happy with,
and there's nothing in it at the moment.
I'm gonna come up to my class name, right
click and go to show context actions and
one of those options now is create tests.
So if I click on that, it's now associated
with J Unit, the library that I've just
installed, and it's gonna call it calculator
test because I'm using the calculator class.
It's gonna add test to the end.
I'm happy with that so I'm gonna go ok.
So what that's done is that's
created a test environment for me.
So what I'm gonna do is to start
with, I need to create a test.
So to do that, I just simply type in test, like
so, now when I press return, it will import the
J Unit library to my class, which is what I want.
I've got a little line under at
the moment cause I've not actually
associated any sort of test with it.
So the test that I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
make sure that two plus  two equals four.
So I'm gonna do void and I'm
gonna call it two plus two.
Oops typing's all off, should equal four like so.
Okay, so two plus two should equal four,
and then I need to use the curly braces.
Now inside my test, I need to create an
instance of the class I'm testing, so I'm
gonna do that so calculator, I'm gonna call
it cow equals new calculator, there you go.
So that's now created an
instance of the calculator class.
So the next thing I'm going to do
is actually use the test itself.
Now the tool that I use for that is
called assert, you can see at the top
there assertions is already imported.
So it knows I'm gonna use that.
So assert, now there's quite a few asserts
that we're, we can use, but I'm gonna use
assert equals like so, so the way this works
is I need to state what it's going to equal.
So we already know it's called
two plus two should equal four.
So the answer is four.
So that's what's going to
be expected the answer four.
Now, what I need to do is how
do we come by that result?
So what we're gonna do is we're gonna use the
cow instance, we're gonna use the method called
add, which is part of Cal, we're gonna bring in
two comma two, so two plus two should equal four.
So here's the the two twos.
Here's the answer and here's
the method we're going to use.
Now you'll see over here on the left
hand side, we've got these arrows.
That means we can run them.
So when run this particular one, it'll say
run calculator test, let's run it, now unlike
before, I'm not gonna have the same output.
Instead, what I'm gonna get are
these little ticks over here.
Okay?
That tells me that it's
passed, I'm happy with that.
Well, hang on a moment.
Let me go back to my main code.
What if I accidentally used the
multiply instead of the plus?
Let's go back to my test
a moment and let's run it.
Well, you'll see that it passes.
So two multiplied by two equals four also.
So this isn't a very good test, or rather
just relying on one test isn't enough.
So let's create another test.
So again, I need to create the test, and
this time I'm gonna do two plus three should
equal five and again, I'm gonna bring in the
calculator, and this time I'm gonna use the
assert equals, and this time it's going to
be five and we need to use the instance of
add, and we are going to have two plus three.
So again, using the same principles
as before, we'll run this whole test.
Now if I click on this one
here, it'll run the whole test.
If I click on this one, it'll only
run this method, so I wanna run
all the tests so let's just do.
Now, unlike before we've got a tick where two plus
two should equal four, but now we've got two plus
three should equal five, and that's failing okay?
So that would cause me to go back to my program
and check the method that we are using and as
you can see, our method is using the multiply.
So let's get rid of that and turn it into a plus.
Then we go back to our test
and we run the test again.
By the way, One thing I didn't mention,
here is what the expected value is,
and here's what the actual value is.
You can also click here to see the difference.
I'm just going to hit run and
now you can see all is right.
We've got the two ticks back.
I'm happy with that.
And so should you be.
Now, one of the questions I often get asked by
students is, Well, what's the point in doing this?
Well, the point is, every time
you run your program, you should
have some kind of test in place.
The more autonomous testing you do, the
quicker it is and more efficient it is for you.
If you have to manually test everything in your
system, you're gonna be wasting a lot of time.
If you can create an autonomous test that
tests for you, it can be done a lot quicker.
If you look down here, you'll see that it says
it took 22 milliseconds to do the two plus
three should equal five and one millisecond
to do the two plus two should equal four.
So as you can see, the process of
it doing is much quicker than you
can now multiply that by a hundred.
It's still not gonna take it a second to do
it, and it's gonna save you a lot of time.
So think about how you test
your products in the future.
I hope you enjoyed this, and if you
did, I look forward to seeing you again.
Thank you.